A Guide to the Papers of Marvin L. Colker
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Marvin L. Colker
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12785
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply to designated files under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.)
Acquisitions
The collection was a gift from Marvin L. Colker to Special Collectionson January 30, 2004; May 4, 2005; January 8, 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
Marvin Leonard Colker was born on March 19, 1927 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and married Hazel Robinson (a graduate of Trinity College, Dublin and the Royal Irish Academy of Music) on November 28, 1959. After earning a B. A. in classics, summa cum laude from the University of Pittsburgh (1948), Colker went to Harvard University for his doctorate (1951). His dissertation was a critical edition of a 12th century Latin epic, the Alexandreisaf Gautier de Chatillon (a poem about the deeds of Alexander the Great). In 1978 he made tremendous revisions to the poem which had been in an inauthentic form based on poor manuscripts.
After two postgraduate fellowships (including a Fulbright fellowship at the University of Paris), Colker joined the faculty of the University of Virginia as instructor of classics (1953), serving as the chairman of the Department of Classics (1963-1968) and becoming a full professor (1967). He also served the University of Dublin in several capacities, including cataloguer of medieval manuscripts and lecture in patristics (1962-1963). He was awarded an honorary Doctor of Letters from Trinity Library, University of Dublin in 1987.
In addition to his edition of Gautier's poem, Colker's publications include Fulcoii Belvacensis Epistolae (1954), Analecta Dublinensia: Three Medieval Latin Texts in the Library of Trinity College, Dublin (1975), and America Rediscovered in the Thirteenth Century (1979). He was a member of Phi Beta Kappa and the Medieval Academy of America, a Guggenheim fellow (1973-1974) and held two Fulbright fellowships, which allowed him travel to England and Ireland for research.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the papers of Marvin L. Colker and is 2,842 items, 7 Hollinger boxes, and 3 linear feet. There is general correspondence of Professor Colker about medieval manuscripts from 1971 to 2006. It is comprised mainly of correspondence with American and European scholars concerned with classical studies and Latin paleography. Also included are computer print outs from his catalog of medieval manuscripts at the Trinity Library, University of Dublin. There are also several manuscripts on the classics including "Fulcoius of Beavais," "Michael of Belluno," and "Six Notes on Gregory the Great," and several book reviews by Dr. Colker. There is also a notebook containing the minutes from meetings of the Washington Society.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- 1971-1989 General Correspondence, 188 items (Box-folder 1:1)
- 1990 General Correspondence, 193 items (Box-folder 1:2)
- 1991 General Correspondence, 227 items (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1992 General Correspondence, 196 items (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1993 General Correspondence, 148 items (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1994 General Correspondence, 87 items (Box-folder 2:2)
- 1995 General Correspondence, 98 items (Box-folder 2:3)
- 1996-1997 General Correspondence, 156 items (Box-folder 2:4)
- 1998 General Correspondence, 140 items (Box-folder 2:5)
- 1999 General Correspondence, 101 items (Box-folder 3:1)
- 2000 General Correspondence, 198 items (Box-folder 3:2)
- 2001 General Correspondence, 176 items (Box-folder 3:3)
- 2002 General Correspondence, 180 items (Box-folder 3:4)
- 2003 General Correspondence, 150 items (Box-folder 3:5)
- 2004 General Correspondence, 201 items (Box-folder 4:1)
- 2005 General Correspondence, 121 items (Box-folder 4:2)
- 2006 General Correspondence, 170 items (Box-folder 4:3)
- n. d. General Correspondence, 50 items (Box-folder 4:4)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 5:1)
  Large group of pages attached by perforated holes from a computer printer
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 5:2)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 5:3)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 5:4)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 6:1)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 6:2)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 6:3)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 6:4)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 7:1)
- n. d.[Manuscripts: Catalog for the Trinity Library in Dublin], 1 item (Box-folder 7:2)
- n. d. Manuscripts "Fulcoius of Beavais", 1 item (Box-folder 7:3)
- n. d. Manuscripts "Michael of Belluno", 1 item (Box-folder 7:4)
- n. d. Manuscripts Miscellaneous, 1 item (Box-folder 7:5)
- n. d. Manuscripts "Six Notes on Gregory the Great", 1 item (Box-folder 7:6)
- n. d. Manuscripts "Vox Classica", 1 item (Box-folder 7:7)
- 1990-1992 Minutes of the Washington Society, 1 notebook (Box-folder 7:8)
- Miscellaneous, 2 items (Box-folder 7:9)
- Reviews, 5 items (Box-folder 7:10)
- Confidential, 39 items (Box-folder 8:1)